The Ching Dynasty during the late 19th century,
十 九 世 紀 末 的 清 帝 國
was a declining empire
是 個 飽 受 內 憂 與 外 悲 的
besieged with domestic and foreign problems.
沒 落 常 國
While the Ching Empire had yet to recover
1851 年 太 平 天 國 之 亂 爆 發
from the Taiping Rebellion in 1851,
清 常 國 還 沒 能 從 內 亂 中 喘 悌
the British-French Alliance in 1858
1858 年 莫 法 聯 軍
forced the Ching Empire to open
又 迫 使 清 常 國 開 放
Anping, Tamsui, Chilung, and Takou ports
安 平 、 淡 水 、 雞 籠 、 打 狗 等
to foreign trade.
台 灣 港 口 與 國 外 通 商
As the ports opened,
台 灣 的 門 戶 洞 開
western merchants, adventurers and missionaries
西 方 的 商 人 、 冒 險 家 、 傳 教 士
all came to Taiwan.
紛 紛 來 到 台 灣
After having been isolated for over a century,
台 灣 和 西 方 世 界
Taiwan and the western world
在 隔 絕 一 個 多 世 紀 之 後
once again met.
再 次 重 逢
However, this time,
此 次 西 方 國 家 再 一 次 到 來
Western countries not only came to trade,
不 只 是 經 濟 買 易 的 往 來
but also brought new cultural impact.
也 同 時 帶 來 了 新 的 文 化 洗 禮
After the ports were opened,
開 港 通 商 之 後
western merchants came to Taiwan
西 方 商 人 紛 紛 來 到 台 灣
to seek business opportunities.
尋 找 商 機
Tataocheng in Taipei
台 北 大 稷 埕
became a trading center for Taiwan tea leaves,
成 為 當 時 台 灣 茬 葉 的 貿 易 中 心
with exports reaching its peak in 1893.
出 口 量 在 1893 年 達 到 顧 峰
Every tea season, the average number of workers
每 逢 茶 季
in and out of Tataocheng ...
平 均 每 天 在 大 稷 埕 進 出 的 茬 工
each day was over 20,000
高 達 兩 萬 人 以 上
while another 10,000 workers
同 時 還 有 近 萬 名 勞 工
shuttled between Tataocheng and Fuchien.
在 大 稷 埕 和 福 建 之 間 穿 梭
Having lived in Taiwan for 32 years,
在 台 灣 居 住 長 達 三 十 二 年 的
British merchant John Dodd
莫 國 商 人 陶 德
could be regarded as the greatest contributor
可 以 說 是
to the modernization of Wulong tea in Taiwan.
台 灣 烏 龍 茶 現 代 化 的 最 大 功 臣
During his stay in Taiwan,
他 在 台 灣 生 活 期 間
Dodd witnessed the flourishing of Tamsui Harbor
見 證 了 淡 水 港 的 興 起
and the prosperity of Tataocheng.
與 大 稷 埕 的 繁 榮
In his diary, Dodd recorded
陶 德 曾 經 在 他 的 日 記 裡
the busy activities there during tea season.
記 載 了 大 稷 埋 當 時 茶 季 的 盛 況
Tataocheng was abound with these “leaves of happiness,”
大 稱 埋 充 滿 這 種 快 樂 之 葉
because they brought big profits.
困 為 它 可 以 帶 來 豐 富 的 收 入
Female tea pickers there were all dressed up beautifully.
大 稷 埕 的 茬 女
They put magnolias on their
個 個 打 扮 得 妖 嬌 美 麗
hair and gold and silver rings on their fingers.
頭 插 玉 蘭 花 手 纏 金 銀 戒 指
They chatted as they picked tea leaves.
邊 揀 茶 邊 談 笑
Droves of female tea pickers
蒯 鶯 燕 燕 的
filled the city with joyous atmosphere.
讓 整 個 城 市 為 之 充 滿 歡 樂 氣 氟
In 1867, Dodd established
1867 年 陶 德 在 ﹁ 艋 船 」
a tea factory in Bangka.
d 設 立 精 製 茶 工 廠
In 1868, he imported Wulong
1868 年 從 福 建 安 溪
from Anhsi in Fuchien,
引 進 烏 龍 茶 苗
and tried to sell Wulong tea in Macao the following year.
隔 年 試 銷 火 龍 茶 到 澳 門
In 1869,
1869 年
he established Dodd & Co. In Tataocheng.
陶 德 在 大 稷 埕 設 立 寶 順 洋 行
In the same year, he used two junks
同 年 用 兩 艘 戎 克 船
to ship 23,000 pounds of Wulong tea
運 載 二 十 萬 三 千 磅 的 烏 龍 茶
to New York for sale.
銷 往 紐 約
The tea became very popular,
廣 意 歡 迎
and other companies quickly followed suit.
於 是 其 他 洋 行 爭 相 跟 進
As a result, tea commerce in Taiwan flourished.
台 灣 芭 商 困 此 興 起
Tataocheng in Taipei became
台 北 大 稷 埋 變 成 了
the hub of western companies and tea merchants.
洋 行 與 茬 商 的 集 中 地
In 1872,
1872 年
from Hsiahai Chenghuang Temple, Tihua Street,
從 霞 海 城 隍 廟 、 迪 化 街
up to the banks of Tamsui River,
以 至 淡 水 河 畔 一 帶
there were six foreign companies
一 共 有 六 家 洋 行
and over 150 tea factories.
和 超 過 一 百 五 十 家 的 製 茬 行
As tea leaves became Taiwan's major export,
茶 葉 成 了 台 灣 外 銷 大 宗
Tataocheng flourished to become
也 從 此 開 啟 台 北 大 稷 埋
a place filled with the aroma of tea and tea flowers.
充 滿 茶 香 與 花 香 的 歲 月
After the ports were opened for trade,
開 港 通 商 以 後
the Ching Empire started to allow missionaries
清 常 國 也 開 始 允 許 西 方 傳 教 士
from the West to spread religion at the ports.
在 通 商 口 岸 傳 教
Since most of the missionaries
被 差 派 來 台 灣 的 傳 教 士
had medical training,
大 部 分 都 受 遇 醫 學 訓 練
the female missionaries
女 性 神 職 人 員
also worked as nurses.
也 都 可 以 身 兼 護 士 職 責
It can be said that the development of churches in Taiwan
台 灣 教 會 的 發 展
was founded on
可 以 說 是 莫 定 在
medical and missionary work
醫 療 傳 道 的 基 礎 上
In 1865, Dr. James L. Maxwell
1865 年 馬 雅 各 醫 生
arrived in Tainan for medical missionary work
來 到 台 南 府 城 行 醫 傳 道
and established the first Presbyterian Church
正 式 開 始 英 國 長 老 教 會
in southern Taiwan.
在 南 台 灣 的 宣 教 工 作
Dr. Maxwell used quinine and surgery
他 利 用 奎 寧 和 外 科 手 術
to treat patients with cataract and bladder stone.
醫 治 了 白 內 障 和 膀 胱 結 石 病 悲
Because his work threatened local Han Chinese physicians,
困 此 造 成 當 地 漢 人 醫 生 的 威 脢
they spread rumors
當 地 醫 生 四 處 散 佈
that Dr. Maxwell used human brain to make opium.
他 利 用 人 腦 製 造 鴉 片 的 謠 言
The rumor caused a public uproar.
引 起 全 城 騷 動
A large mob
大 批 民 眾
surrounded his residence in Kanhsi Street
包 圍 他 在 看 西 街 的 住 所
and destroyed the church and clinic.
拆 毀 禮 拐 堂 和 醫 館
To prevent escalation of the uproar,
為 了 避 免 騷 動 擴 大
city officials ordered Doctor Maxwell to leave the city.
官 府 下 令 他 離 開 府 城
Less than 24 days after starting his missionary work,
行 醫 傳 道 不 到 二 十 四 天 的 馬 雅 各
Dr. Maxwell was forced
被 迫 遷 徙 到
to move to a place protected by the British consulate,
有 莫 國 領 事 保 護 的 地 方
which was present-day Chichin in Kaohsiung,
也 就 是 今 天 高 雁 的 旗 津
where he continued his medical and missionary work.
繼 續 醫 療 與 傳 道 的 工 作
In 1870,
到 了 1870 年
Dr. Maxwell's missionary effort
馬 雅 各 播 下 的 福 音 種 子
started to bear fruit.
已 經 產 生 效 果
Some of his patients
一 些 病 悌
started to praise his good work,
被 馬 雅 各 醫 生 醫 治 後 到 處 宣 揚
and more patients came to see him.
求 醫 者 也 越 來 越 多
They brought the Gospel they heard in the clinic
並 且 把 在 醫 館 所 聽 到 的 福 音
back to their villages.
帶 回 鄉 里 傳 揚
This was the beginning of
成 為 之 後
the spread of churches in southern Taiwan.
南 台 灣 各 地 教 會 的 種 子
On March 9, 1872,
1872 年 3 月 9 日
the Sea Dragon, which was traveling
航 行 於 台 灣 海 峽 的
in the Taiwan Strait, sailed into Tamsui Harbor.
﹁ 海 龍 號 」 輪 船 進 入 淡 水 港
A Canadian youth traveling onboard
船 上 有 一 位 加 拿 大 青 年
fell in love with Tamsui and
對 淡 水 風 光 一 見 鍾 情
decided to dedicate his life to this land.
決 定 為 這 塊 土 地 付 出 他 的 一 生
His subsequent medical, educational,
他 就 是 後 來 以 醫 療 、 教 育
and missionary work in Taiwan
與 宣 教 工 作
had significant influence on Taiwan's culture
對 台 灣 文 化 風 貌
This young man was Dr. George Mackay.
造 成 影 響 的 馬 偕 博 士
There seems to be an invisible line
好 像 有 一 條 無 形 的 線
that draws me to this beautiful island.
牽 引 我 到 這 美 麗 之 島
Dr. Mackay wrote in his diary.
馬 偕 在 日 記 中 描 過
Dr. Mackay had been sent by Canada's Presbyterian Church
他 當 年 被 加 拿 大 長 老 教 會
to do missionary work in Taiwan.
差 派 來 台 灣 宣 教
When I arrived at the estuary of Tamsui River
巿 哲 ﹍ 孔 匕 4 【 【 【 一 曰 勺 l 奀 ﹍ |
in northern Taiwan, I looked to the north and south,
我 舉 目 向 北 向 南
then gazed at the green mountains inland.
然 後 向 內 陸 遙 望 青 翠 的 山 嶺
I felt spiritually satisfied
心 靈 非 常 的 滿 足
and peaceful.
心 神 安 寧 清 靜
A clear voice was telling me:
有 一 股 明 確 的 聲 音 對 著 我 說
This is the place
此 地 就 是 了
Dr. Mackay used Tamsui as his base for missionary work
馬 偕 以 淡 水 為 根 據 地
in northern Taiwan and provided medical services
在 台 灣 北 部 傳 教
to supplement his missionary work.
以 醫 療 服 務 來 輔 佐 宣 教 工 作
Dr. Mackay understood that
馬 偕 瞭 解
he must first learn to speak fluent Taiwanese to be able
他 引 須 先 學 會 流 利 的 台 灣 話
to establish a foundation for spreading the Gospel.
才 能 讓 福 音 工 作 在 台 灣 紮 根
On Jan. 25.
1 月 25 日 發 聲 吟 漢 文
I learned 100 words and chanted the Chinese aloud.
又 再 學 習 了 一 百 個 新 單 字
March 4th
3 月 4 日
I exerted myself to read Chinese books diligently,
我 勉 勵 自 己 勤 奮 讀 漢 文 書
and reviewed all that I've learned before.
把 以 前 所 學 的 都 一 再 複 習
At the same time, I added 100 new words.
同 時 又 添 了 一 百 個 新 字
Currently, I know 240 characters by heart.
現 在 二 百 十 四 個 部 首
Dr. Mackay traveled throughout Taiwan
馬 偕 深 入 台 灣 各 角 落
living together with the locals
與 本 地 人 生 活 在 一 起
in Wuku, Taoyuan, Chungli, and Hsinkang.
從 五 股 、 桃 園 、 中 塔 、 新 港
He visited aborigines in Neishe for missionary work.
並 且 深 入 內 社 原 住 民 部 落 傳 教
Many people opposed Christianity.
許 多 人 很 反 對 基 督 教
Because they don't have medicine for their sickness,
但 回 生 病 沒 藥 醫
they came to me, a foreigner.
而 來 求 助 於 我 這 個 外 國 人
From being enemies we became friends.
於 是 我 們 由 敵 人 變 成 朋 友
The Han Chinese were resilient.
漢 人 具 有 強 韌 的 神 經
They can endure the pain from surgery.
他 們 可 以 怒 受 開 刀 的 痛 苺
It's really amazing
實 在 令 人 驚 奇
Since 1873,
從 1873 年 以 來
in 30 years of medical service in Taiwan,
馬 偕 在 台 灣 行 醫 三 十 年
Dr. Mackay extracted at least 21,000 teeth.
至 少 拔 了 兩 萬 一 千 積 牙 齒
On March 18, 1873,
1873 年 3 月 18 日
a visitor arrived at the Tamsui church to visit
一 位 稀 客 走 進 淡 水 教 堂
Rev. Mackay, who had succeed in his missionary work.
拜 花 傳 教 初 具 成 果 的 馬 偕 政 師
The visitor was Rev. William Campbell,
他 就 是 在 1871 年
who was sent by the English Presbyterian Church
被 莫 國 長 老 教 會
to do missionary work in Taiwan.
差 派 來 台 灣 傳 教 的 甘 為 霍 牧 師
These two missionaries
這 兩 位 傳 教 士
became the two underpinnings
在 未 來 成 為 長 老 教 會
of the Presbyterian Church,
在 南 、 北 台 灣 宣 教 工 作 的
which spread Christianity in southern and northern Taiwan
兩 大 磊 石
Dr. Mackay was a diligent traveler.
馬 偕 勤 於 旅 行
He traveled to Hsuehshan,
從 雪 山 探 險
the plains of Lanyang, the east coast in Hualien
深 入 蘭 陽 平 原 、 花 東 海 岸
and the three islets in the north.
甚 至 在 北 方 三 小 島
Despite the many dangers and difficulties,
經 歷 許 多 危 難
Dr. Mackay remained determined to do missionary work.
仍 然 不 改 他 宣 教 的 決 心
Rev. Campbell and I went together to Wukukeng,
甘 牧 師 與 我 一 同 至 五 股 坑
Chouli, Bangka, Chungli,
洲 裡 、 艋 船 、 中 壢
Chuchian, Hsinkang, and Neishe.
竹 壑 、 新 港 、 內 社
From Neishe, Rev. Campbell proceeded north,
甘 政 師 由 內 社 繼 續 南 下
while I ventured deep into the mountains.
而 我 則 進 入 深 山 地 區
Mountain trails were rugged and the grasses were tall.
山 路 崎 嶇 茅 草 又 高
After much difficulty, we arrived at a summit,
好 不 容 易 來 到 一 座 山 峰
and shouted.
我 們 大 聲 呼 叫
Soon, I heard gun shots from the base of the mountain.
不 久 我 就 聽 到 山 下 的 槍 聲
Another team of raw barbarians were waiting.
又 有 一 隊 生 番 在 等 著 我 們
I've spent 8 pleasant days with Mr. Mackay
﹍ 我 和 馬 偕 先 生 渡 過 八 天 愉 恨 皓 時 光
and now I see much hope for the future.
見 到 充 滿 希 望 的 行 動 即 將 開 展
I now realized that I should return to the original missionary
困 此 希 望 能 回 到 原 來 的 駟 點 彰 化
Walking in the big cities,
走 在 大 城 市 裡
we often meet blind people.
我 們 不 時 會 遇 到 盲 人
Many Chinese suffered from
中 國 人 深 受 天 花
small pox and poor hygiene.
以 及 不 良 衛 生 習 慣 的 危 害
So we are not really surprised.
對 此 我 們 並 不 慚 到 訝 異
Most blind people are beggars
盲 人 似 乎 多 半 當 乞 丐
or worked as fortunetellers.
或 以 算 命 為 業
Some worked as threshers or step tread mill to make their living.
也 有 些 靠 打 穀 或 跺 水 車 維 生
As the missionary work expanded,
隨 著 傳 教 士 的 福 音 工 作 的 展 開
Dr. Mackay established the
1883 年 馬 偕 也 在 淡 水 創 建 了
Oxford College in 1883
理 學 堂 大 書 院
and introduced western-type education.
引 進 西 洋 式 教 育
Dr. Mackay later established
後 來 又 成 立 專 收 女 子 的
the all-girl Tamsui Girls' School.
淡 水 女 學 堂
In 1885, Rev. Campbell,
1885 年
who was doing missionary work in the Tainan area,
在 台 南 地 區 宣 教 的 甘 為 霍
established the first school
開 設 了 台 灣 當 時
for the blind in Taiwan.
唯 一 的 盲 人 學 校
The school used Roman-script
利 用 羅 馬 拼 音 字 母 的
Braille printing
凶 字 版 印 刷
to publish five books for the blind.
為 盲 人 出 版 了 五 本
The Braille Gospel and missionary booklets were
點 字 版 的 福 音 書 和 傳 教 小 冊
the first Braille books for the blind in Taiwan, and were
這 是 台 灣 第 第 一 批 的 盲 人 點 字 書
the precursor of education for the blind in Taiwan.
開 啟 台 灣 盲 人 教 育 的 先 沼
In 1913, Rev. Campbell published the New Dictionary
1913 年
of the Vernacular or Spoken Language of Amoy
甘 為 霍 出 版 ﹁ 廈 門 音 新 字 典 」
which is still widely in use today.
到 現 在 仍 然 被 廣 泛 流 傳 使 用
In 1861, British Vice Consul
1861 年 來 到 台 灣 的
Robert Swinhoe became
莢 國 副 領 事 史 溫 俗
the first foreign consular representative to Taiwan.
是 外 國 第 一 位 駐 台 的 外 交 官
He was also a typical English naturalist
他 同 時 也 是 維 多 利 亞 時 代
of the Victorian Age.
莢 國 博 物 學 家 的 一 個 典 型
From the perspective of modern taxonomy,
就 現 代 生 物 分 類 學 的 觀 點 來 說
Swinhoe was the first
他 是 第 一 個 有 系 統 的
to systematically perform
實 地 調 查 、 紀 錄 、 掌 集 標 本
on-site studies, document, collect samples,
和 發 表 台 灣 動 植 物 相 的
and publish in writing Taiwan's fauna and flora.
先 驅 性 人 物
In April 1862,
1862 年 4 月
Swinhoe traveled along upstream Tahan River and
史 溫 侯 沿 著 大 漢 溪 上 溯
arrive at Kueihui commune,
拗 達 奎 輝 社
which is present-day Fuhsing Village in Taoyuan,
也 就 是 今 天 桃 園 的 復 興 鄉
to investigate the site and collect samples.
實 地 調 查 及 採 集 標 本
In July of the same year,
同 年 7 月 並 且 發 表
he published his pioneering research into the history
台 灣 哺 乳 類
of Taiwan's mammals:
研 究 史 上 的 開 山 作 品
On the Mammals of the Island of Formosa.
﹁ 台 灣 哺 乳 類 研 究 史 」
Of the 62 known mammalian species
在 目 前 所 知 道 的
in Taiwan today,
台 灣 六 十 二 種 哺 乳 動 物 當 中
Swinhoe recorded 27,
他 紀 錄 了 二 十 七 種
11 of which were new species
其 中 十 一 種 為 新 種
that he studied and named.
都 由 他 親 自 確 認 命 名
At around 1863, Swinhoe published the
1863 年 前 後 史 溫 侯 發 表 了
The Ornithology of Formosa.
﹁ 福 爾 摩 沙 鳥 類 學 」
Among the 458 known species
在 台 灣 現 有 紀 錄 的
of birds in Taiwan today,
四 百 五 十 八 種 鳥 類 當 中
Swinhoe discovered a total of
史 溶 侯 所 發 現 的 共 計
226 species.
兩 百 二 十 六 種
The Swinhoe's Blue Pheasant
他 在 淡 水 內 地 山 區
found in the mountain areas of inner Tamsui
所 發 現 的 藍 腹 瞜
was named after him.
就 是 以 史 溶 侯 來 命 名
Swinhoe's discoveries secured his place in ornithology.
奚 定 了 他 在 鳥 類 學 界 的 地 位
Another British, Charles Darwin,
同 樣 是 莢 國 人 的 達 爾 文
had earlier published
也 在 那 之 前 才 發 表 了 著 作
The Origin of Species.
﹁ 物 種 原 始 」
It is during this time when the flora and fauna in Taiwan
這 時 候 台 灣 的 動 植 物
gradually became known to the West.
才 漸 漸 被 西 方 認 識
Taiwan's natural history and ethnographies also became
台 灣 自 然 史 和 民 族 誌
important world assets.
也 成 為 世 界 重 要 的 資 產
In February 1866,
1866 年 2 月
Swinhoe traveled upstream along Kaoping River
史 溫 侯 沿 著 高 屏 溪 溯 溪 而 上
and arrived near present-day Liukuei and Hsuehshan
拗 達 今 天 的 公 龜 、 雪 山 附 近
to study its biology.
做 實 地 生 物 調 查
This would be his last extended field study
這 是 他 在 台 灣 停 留 期 間
during his stay in Taiwan.
最 後 一 次 較 長 時 間 的 田 野 調 查
In his later published writings,
在 他 後 來 發 表 的 文 章 中
he described with precision the broad-leaf forests in the low-altitude
曾 經 精 確 地 描 繪 百 年 前
mountain areas in southern Taiwan over 100 years ago
南 台 灣 低 地 山 區 闊 葉 林 的 景 別
Swinhoe also eulogized the beautiful island of Taiwan,
並 且 透 過 對 自 然 生 物 的 禮 讚
praising its nature and ecology
歌 頌 台 灣 這 個 美 麗 之 島
In the offshore Takou,
在 近 海 的 打 狗
there were butterfly paths like rivers.
曾 發 現 像 河 流 一 樣 的 蠑 道
And numberable wobblers in the forest.
林 中 也 有 數 不 清 的 鳥 鳴
Formosa is really a natural paradise.
福 爾 摩 沙 真 是 自 然 世 界 的 天 堂
On Nov. 6, 1871
1871 年 11 月 6 日
a tribute transport ship from Miyako Island in Ryukyu
一 艘 璉 球 宮 古 島 的 納 貢 船
encountered a storm at sea,
在 海 上 遇 到 風 暫
drifting to Hengchun Peninsula in southeast Taiwan.
漂 流 到 台 灣 東 南 恆 春 半 島 的
The ship capsized
八 瑤 灣 附 近
near Payao Bay.
船 隻 翻 覆
Three persons drowned,
三 人 溺 死
while 66 reached the shore.
六 十 六 人 上 岸
They lost their way and ventured into Kaoshihfo
誤 入 排 灣 族 高 士 佛 社 的 地 界
commune of the Paiwan tribe.
由 於 言 語 不 通 產 生 誤 會
Because of miscommunication due to the language barrier,
這 批 璋 球 人
54 of this batch of Ryukyu people
後 來 被 排 灣 族 的 高 士 佛 社
were killed by the Paiwan tribe.
殺 死 了 五 十 四 人
Only 12 were able to escape
只 有 十 二 人 脫 逃 到
to seek protection in the Hakka village of Paolichuang.
客 家 村 落 保 力 庄 尋 求 庇 護
The killing of the Ryukyu shipwreck survivors was an
這 個 困 為 船 難 所 引 發 的
incident that the Ching administration
琉 球 漂 民 虐 殺 事 件
regarded as having happened outside of their jurisdiction.
在 清 國 ﹕ 宮 府 背 表 示 事 屬 化 外
The passive attitude of the Ching administration
無 權 千 涉 的 消 極 態 度 之 後
gave Japan the opportunity
正 好 為 日 本 提 供 了 一 個
to announce sovereignty over Ryukyu. Japan also sent
宣 示 琉 球 宗 主 權 的 機 會
troops to southern Taiwan to punish the raw barbarians.
日 本 藉 機 出 兵 南 台 灣 懲 罰 生 番
On May 7, 1874,
1874 年 5 月 7 日
Japanese soldiers landed in Langchiao Bay in Hengchun,
日 軍 在 恆 春 半 島 的 琳 憲 灣
which is present-day
也 就 是 今 天
Sheliao near Checheng, Hengchun.
恒 春 車 城 附 近 的 射 寧 登 陸
On May 18,
18 日
a small platoon of Japanese soldiers arrived at
一 小 隊 日 本 兵 來 到 恆 春 四 重 溪
Shihchung River in Hengchun to survey the Shihmen area.
石 門 一 帶 偵 查
They were attacked by residents of Mutan commune.
遭 到 牡 丹 社 人 攻 擊
On May 22, 1874,
1874 年 5 月 22 日
the Battle of Shihmen erupted,
爆 發 了 ﹁ 石 門 之 役 」 的 激 戰
and the Japanese expeditionary force
日 本 遠 征 軍
showed its enormous military superiority.
藉 此 展 現 強 大 的 軍 力
The head of Mutan commune and his son died in the battle.
牡 丹 社 頭 目 父 子 戰 死
The Mutan residents continued their strong resistance.
但 是 牡 丹 社 人 依 然 頑 強 拗 抗
As the Battle of Shihmen
正 當 石 門 之 戰
raged on,
打 得 如 火 姊 茬 之 際
lieutenant-general Tsugumichi Saigou
日 本 陸 軍 中 將 西 鄉 從 道
landed in Langchiao Bay with a large number of soldiers.
親 自 率 領 大 軍 從 琅 嶠 灣 登 陸
Japanese victory in the Battle of Shihmen
日 軍 石 門 之 役 的 勝 利
shocked communities in Langchiao.
使 得 珋 嶠 各 社 驚 慌
To protect themselves,
尋 求 自 保
on May 25,
5 月 25 日
members of the Alliance of the 16 Langchiao Communes,
﹁ 璉 嶠 下 十 六 社 」 聯 盟 成 員
the head of Soavari commune Isa,
射 麻 裏 社 的 頭 目 伊 厝
and the head of Chushu commune Young Tauketok,
以 及 豬 澇 束 社 頭 目 小 卓 杞 篙
under direction of the Japanese,
在 日 方 主 導 下
led the other tribal leaders
率 領 其 他 部 落 頭 目 出 面
to meet with
和 日 軍 都 督 西 鄉 從 道
Saigou for a second time.
舉 行 二 度 會 談
At that time, the aborigines in the Langchiao area,
當 時 世 居 於 南 台 灣 琅 嶠 地 區
in southern Taiwan, which is present-day
也 就 是 今 天 恆 春 半 島 的 原 住 民
Hengchun Peninsula, lived as 18 separate tribal
以 十 八 個 獨 立 個 體 部 落 的 型 態
communities scattered all over the region.
散 居 於 各 地
Although Isa and Young Tauketok
伊 厝 與 小 卓 杞 篤
were elected as
雖 然 被 共 同 推 舉 為
leaders of the Langchiao 18 communes,
﹁ 琳 嘯 下 十 八 社 」 的 領 袞
in reality,
但 是 實 質 上
they did not have power
他 們 對 其 它 鄧 落
to restrain the other tribes.
並 沒 有 絕 對 的 約 束 力
The purpose of the Japanese in the talk
日 軍 這 次 會 談 的 用 意
was to unite the members
在 刻 意 聯 合
of the Langchiao commune alliance
﹁ 璉 嶠 下 十 六 社 」 聯 盟 成 員
and include the prime culprit of the Ryukyu killing incident,
將 瑰 球 漂 民 事 件 的 元 兇
which was the intrepid Mutan commune,
高 士 佛 社 和 十 八 社 中 勢 力 最 大
the most powerful among the Kaoshihfo and 18 communes,
也 最 強 悍 的 牡 丹 社
as target of military attacks.
一 起 列 為 討 伐 對 真
Members of the Langchiao commune alliance
﹁ 璉 嶠 下 十 公 社 」 的 聯 盟 部 落
should not protect the Mutan people,
不 得 庇 護 牡 丹 社 人
and should help the Japanese soldiers capture Mutan
並 應 協 助 日 軍 進 捕
warriors who had escaped into their commune to
逃 入 勢 力 範 圍 的 牡 丹 社 戰 士
show loyalty to the alliance between both parties.
以 示 雙 方 結 盟 的 誠 意
I guarantee the Kueitsaichiao communes will cease to view
我 保 證 龜 仔 角 等 社 不 敢 再 仍 視 日 軍
the Japanese as enemies.
萬 一 部 落 再 有 攻 擊 日 軍 事 件 發 生
Should any tribe attack the Japanese soldiers in the future,
我 保 證 親 自 引 領 日 軍 討 伐
I will personally lead their army to suppress the attack.
只 要 聯 盟 成 員 遵 守 上 述 要 求
The alliance members should abide by the above demands
為 了 避 免 誤 殺 各 社
To prevent killings by mistake, all you have to do is raise the flag.
只 要 高 舉 保 護 旗 就 可 平 安 無 事
On June 1, 1874,
1874 年 6 月 1 日
Saigou led 1360 soldiers to
西 鄉 從 道 率 領 一 千 三 百 六 十 人
attack Mutan commune from three directions:
從 石 門 、 竹 社 、 楓 港
Shihmen, Chushe, and Fengkang.
兵 分 三 路 央 擊 牡 丹 社
On June 3,
6 月 3 日
Japanese soldiers captured Mutan commune.
日 軍 攻 破 牡 丹 社
Faced with superior Japanese military strength,
在 日 軍 像 勢 武 力 下
Mutan commune finally surrendered.
牡 丹 社 終 於 歸 降
The 18 Langchiao communes
﹁ 珋 嶠 下 十 八 社 」
submitted themselves under Japanese occupational force.
完 全 臣 服 在 日 本 佔 領 軍 手 下
After the Meiji Restoration,
﹁ 壯 丹 社 事 件 」
the Mutan Incident was
是 自 明 治 維 新 以 來
the first time that Japan sent their soldiers abroad.
日 本 首 次 對 外 出 兵
Because the incident
困 此 事 件 爆 發 之 後
attracted the attention of the British and American media,
引 起 莫 美 國 際 媒 體 的 注 意
British diplomat to China Thomas Wade
清 日 兩 國 的 對 峙
acted as mediator between the Ching Dynasty and Japan.
經 過 莢 國 公 使 威 妥 瑪 居 間 蒙 旋
A treaty was signed,
清 日 二 常 國 互 換 條 款
which called for the withdrawal of the Japanese soldiers
日 軍 撤 退
and compensation from the Ching administration.
清 國 賠 款 而 落 幕
One year after the Mutan Incident,
牡 丹 社 事 件 後 第 二 年
on Jan. 12, 1875,
1875 年 1 月 12 日
the Ching Emperor Tungchih passed away,
清 帝 國 同 治 皇 帝 逝 世
and the Empress Dowager officially came into power.
慈 禧 太 后 正 式 掌 握 清 常 國 大 權
The military invasion resulting from the Ryukyu shipwreck
困 船 難 引 起 的 軍 事 入 侵 事 付
finally came to a close
終 於 落 幕
Yet a battle of a larger scale
但 一 場 更 大 的 歷 史 戰 役
loomed.
已 經 悄 悄 向 台 灣 逼 近
10 years after the Mutan Incident,
牡 丹 社 事 件 發 生 之 後 十 年
Taiwan, for no reason, was drawn into another
台 灣 又 無 端 捲 入 一 場
war between imperialist empires.
常 國 主 義 的 爭 奪 戰 爭
In Indochina,
在 中 南 半 島
the French were plotting to extend their power into
法 國 正 處 心 積 慮 的 想 將 勢 力
the Ching vassal state Annan.
伸 入 清 國 的 藩 屬 國 安 南
To force the hand of the Ching Empire,
為 了 迪 使 清 國 屈 服
the French decided to attack China's commercial ports.
法 國 決 定 攻 擊 清 國 的 通 商 港 口
As a result, Taiwan became
於 是 台 灣 也 成 了
a battleground in the Sino-French war.
﹁ 清 法 戰 爭 」 的 戰 場
At that time, Liu Ming-chuan
當 時
was dispatched to oversee military affairs to Taiwan,
劉 銘 傳 剛 被 派 到 台 灣 督 辦 軍 務
where he augmented the defense of
他 在 雞 籠 、 淡 水 、 澎 湖 等 地
Chilung, Tamsui, and Penghu.
洨 兵 加 強 防 守
Amedee Courbet, admiral of the Far East French fleet,
而 法 國 遠 東 艦 隊 總 司 令 孤 拔
was under orders to capture Chilung and the coal mines.
奉 命 佔 領 雞 籠 以 及 附 近 煤 礦 場
On Aug. 26, 1884,
1884 年 8 月 26 日
the Ching Empire declared war against France.
清 常 國 向 法 國 宣 戰
On Oct. 1, 1884,
10 月 1 日
Courbet led ten battleships
孫 拔 親 自 率 領 十 艘 軍 艦
and over 2000 marines and artillery
以 及 從 越 南 增 援 的
reinforcements from Vietnam
陸 戰 隊 與 砲 兵 等 兩 千 餘 人
and launched a second attack on Chilung.
對 雞 籠 進 行 第 二 次 進 攻
Courbet's retinue at the time
當 時 隨 佾 在 孤 拔 將 軍 身 邊 的
was Orderly Jean,
傳 令 兵 Jean
who recorded his experience
曾 經 在 這 場 遠 東 戰 役 中
in this battle in the Far East.
以 書 信 記 下 了 他 的 親 身 經 歷
Our cannons destroyed everything,
我 們 用 大 砲 摩 毀 所 有 東 西
but the Ching army quickly rebuilt their defense line.
但 清 軍 又 重 建 防 線
It was like a spider reweaving its web.
就 像 蜘 蛛 重 織 被 扯 破 的 網 一 樣
There were over 6000 Ching defenders.
而 且 有 六 千 多 個 清 兵 防 守
During the Sino-French War,
清 法 戰 爭 期 間
British tea merchant
莢 國 茶 商 陶 德
John Dodd in his diary
在 日 記 中 ly
described the French landing in Hsientung, Chilung,
描 述 當 時 法 軍 自 雞 籠 仙 洞 登 陸
and Liu's hasty abandon of the defense.
劉 銘 傳 倉 皇 棄 守 的 情 景
The catastrophe.
情 況 嚴 重 囉
French troops landed in Kelang on October 1st.
法 軍 在 10 月 1 日 登 陸 雞 籠
Although they have been compelled twice by the garrison troops to draw back,
雛 被 守 軍 逼 退 兩 次
The Ching troops were gradually pushed back.
清 軍 節 節 敗 退
There were many casualties in the battle,
死 傷 慮 重 而 且 不 少 人 被 俘
Liu Ming-chuan finally ordered a retreat to Tataocheng and Tamsui.
劉 銘 傳 終 於 下 令 撤 退
On Oct. 2,
10 月 2 日
over 1000 French landed and captured Chilung Harbor,
法 軍 千 餘 人 登 陸 佔 領 雞 籠 港
making it their official stronghold in Taiwan.
正 式 在 台 灣 陸 地 上 取 得 據 點
By this time, Liu had
這 時 劉 銘 傳 已 經 將 不 少
transferred troops defending Chilung
原 本 防 衛 雞 籠 的 部 隊
to Tamsui.
抽 調 到 淡 水
General Sun Kai-hua of the Hsiang army defending Tamsui
驛 守 淡 水 的 湘 軍 孫 開 華 將 軍
predicted a French attack, so he loaded boats with rocks and
預 測 法 軍 會 來 侵 犯
sunk them at the Tamsui River estuary.
於 是 在 淡 水 河 口 載 石 沈 船
He also laid water mines at the harbor to prevent
封 港 並 佈 下 水 雷
the French from pushing deep into the city of Taipei.
以 防 止 法 軍 長 趨 直 入 台 北 城
At 10 a.m,, Oct. 8, 1884,
1884 年 10 月 8 日 上 午 十 點
Courbet sent seven French warships
孟 拔 果 然 派 出 七 艙 法 國 戰 艦
to attack Tamsui.
砲 擊 淡 水
Some 600 French marines
六 百 名 陸 戰 隊
landed on the northeastern coast of Shalun
強 行 登 陸 沒 岩 東 北 海 岸
to defuse the mines.
打 算 破 壞 水 雷
In his letter, Orderly Jean,
親 自 參 與 這 場 淡 水 浴 血 戰 的
who was part of this Tamsui landing,
法 國 傳 令 兵 Jean 曾 經 在 信 中
recounted his experience:
回 憶 他 當 時 的 親 身 經 歷
We've landed for the moment.
我 們 暫時 已 上 了 岸
It was a sand dune.
那 是 一 片 沙 坎
Our boots sunk in the fine sand every step of the way.
腳 下 的 細 沙 使 軍 鞋 一 踏 上 就 陷 住
Suddenly, a volley of bullets were fired at us.
突 然 眼 前 飛 來 一 串 齊 發 的 子 彈
An astounding number of Chinese
多 得 出 奇 的 一 大 票 中 國 人
appeared from all directions.
突 然 從 四 面 八 方 湧 出
The Ching army was led by a General Sun.
這 些 清 軍 是 由 一 位 孫 將 軍 指 揮
I don't know how many stars he has.
我 也 不 知 道 掛 幾 顆 星 的
When we bombarded his fort,
我 們 炸 毀 他 的 堡 壘 時
he was inside drinking champagne and having lunch.
他 還 正 邊 喝 香 檳 邊 吃 午 餐
While the Ching and French armies were
當 清 、 法 兩 軍 殺 得 昏 天 暗 地
entangled in a fierce battle,
死 去 活 來 時
90 foreigners
共 有 九 十 名 外 僑
based in elevated locations in
分 據 在 淡 水 紅 毛 城
Hungmaocheng in Tamsui and Pitsaitou
鼻 仔 頭 等 制 高 點
watched the battle across the water.
隔 岸 觀 火 評 論 戰 況
British tea merchant Dodd
莢 國 茶 商 陶 德
was among this group of onlookers
也 在 這 群 人 行 列 當 中
who were witnesses to this fierce battle.
為 這 場 激 烈 的 戰 役 留 下 見 證
All the foreigners believed that the gallant general,
外 僑 都 相 俸 英 勇 的 孫 開 華 將 軍
Suen Kai-hua, would protect them from the war
不 但 不 會 遭 到 無 情 戰 火 的 摩 殘
regardless of the outcome.
不 管 最 後 勝 利 與 否 ﹣ 都 將 取 到 朝 廷 的 封 賞
He has been quartered here since 1874,
他 從 1874 年 日 本 侵 台 的
following the Mutan Sha Incident,
牡 丹 社 事 件 起 便 駭 紮 在 此
As a general, he was widely loved and respected.
治 軍 甚 嚴 待 兵 姜 子
Under General Sun's command,
在 孫 開 華 將 軍 的 指 揮 下
1500 Ching soldiers and Taiwanese militiamen
一 千 五 百 名 清 軍 和 台 勇
lay in four routes to ambush
分 四 路 埋 伏 前 後 失 擊
and repelled the French army.
摘 退 法 軍
Sun and his troops have filled a glorious page in Taiwan's history.
寫 下 台 灣 史 上 光 輝 的 紀 錄
On Oct. 12, as his church was destroyed,
10 月 12 號 因 為 教 堂 被 碌
Dr. Mackay and his family
馬 偕 醫 師 攜 常 家 眸
took refuge in Hong Kong.
前 往 香 港 避 難
Defeated in Tamsui for the second time,
淡 水 的 二 度 挫 折
French realized that their objective
使 法 軍 發 現
couldn't be achieved through military action alone.
單 靠 軍 事 行 動 並 不 能 達 到 目 的
The French then announced a blockade of Taiwan,
於 是 宣 布 封 鎖 台 灣
prohibiting other foreign ships
禁 止 任 何 國 家 的 船 艦
from entering the seas of Taiwan.
進 入 台 灣 海 域
On Oct. 23, 1884, the French
1884 年 10 月 23 日
government authorized its fleet in the Far East
法 國 遠 東 艦 隊 受 法 國 政 府 授 權
to run a blockade of Formosa island
封 鎖 福 爾 摩 沙 島
I, Admiral Amedee Courbet
本 人
of the French fleet,
海 軍 中 將 法 國 遠 東 艦 隊 總 司 令 孤 拔
view the current situation
鑒 於 目 前 法 清 戰 爭 狀 態
and announce the following:
茲 宣 告 如 下
Starting Oct. 23, 1884,
自 1884 年 10 月 23 日 起
from north latitude 21°50” at Erhluanpi,
從 鵡 鸞 齁 北 緯 21 度 50 分
east longitude 118°32”,
東 經 118 度 32 分
passing the eastern and northern coastal areas
經 西 部 及 北 部 海 岸 到 蘇 澳 南 方
to the south of Su-ao, north latitude 24°30”,
北 緯 24 恭 嵇 24 度 30 分
east longitude 119°35”,
東 經 119 度 35 分
the ports and bays of Taiwan
台 灣 各 港 埠 、 海 灣
will be blocked by the French navy.
昀 由 法 國 海 軍 封 鎖
Ships of neutral country should unload the merchandise
中 立 國 船 艦 應 於 三 日 內 完 成 卸 貨
within three days, and leave the blockade area.
並 退 出 封 鎖 區
Attempts to violate the blockade will be dealt with
鈍 圖 侵 犯 上 述 封 鎖 的 船 艦
according to international law and existing treaties.
將 依 國 際 法 及 現 行 條 約 處 理
So, a state of anarchy befell northern Taiwan.
北 台 灣 頓 時 陷 入 無 政 府 狀 態
Antagonism against foreigners caused riots and looting.
仇 外 情 鰤 引 起 暴 動 、 搶 劫
Churches were burned and destroyed.
教 堂 愛 被 波 及 燒 毀
Two months after the blockade,
台 灣 遭 受 軍 事 封 鎖 兩 個 月 後
British tea merchant Dodd
莢 國 茶 商 陶 德
was forced to evacuate along with other foreigners.
也 被 迫 隨 著 外 僑
Dodd left his tea company in Tataocheng,
撤 離 大 稻 埋 茬 行
and sought refuge inside the British consulate in Tamsui
到 淡 水 的 莫 國 領 事 館 避 難
In his diary, he described
他 在 日 記 中 曾 經 描 連
the deserted Tataocheng
當 時 空 盪 冷 清 的 大 稱 埕
and his despair for the loss incurred
與 賤 易 被 迫 停 頓
after his tea trade ended.
他 平 白 遭 恆 巨 大 損 失 的 無 奈 心 情
This was again another day full of doubt,
又 是 一 個 充 滿 疑 悲 、 臆 測
guessing, and rumors.
蒲 傳 的 日 子
Everybody felt more and more helpless in these depressing times,
每 個 人 對 這 種 沉 悶 的 時 光
more and more dissatisfied.
越 來 越 不 滿
If people knew when the blockade would end,
若 脊 預 知 封 鎖 日 期
maybe it would help relax the mood.
或 許 還 稍 能 舒 緩 這 種 情 鰹
December 16.
12 月 16 日
There was only one German battleship accompanying us in the harbor,
港 外 只 剩 ﹁ 德 倫 凡 得 號 」 戰 艦 伴 隨 我 們
but we were still quite busy.
但 我 們 可 沒 閒 著
With great enthusiasm, we organized a billiard competition,
困 運 動 的 興 致 大 發
To force the hand of the Ching Dynasty,
為 了 迫使 清 國 退 讓
the French next captured Pescadores.
法 軍 進 一 步 佔 領 澎 湖
The Ching and French
清 、 法 兩 國 終 於 在
finally on June 6, 1885
1885 年 6 月 9 日 達 成 協 議
signed the Treaty of Tientsin.
簽 訂 ﹁ 天 津 條 約 」
The Ching Empire relinquished its vassal state Annan,
清 常 國 失 去 朝 貢 國 安 南
and the war finally ended.
結 束 了 這 場 戰 爭
On June 11, 1885,
1885 年 6 月 11 日
Admiral Amedee Courbet of the French fleet,
法 國 遠 東 艦 隊 總 司 令 孫 拔
was infected with cholera
困 為 愁 染 霍 亂
and died on the battleship Bayard.
病 死 於 拜 逸 戰 艦 上
The French withdrew
法 軍 撤 退
leaving behind a devastated Chilung.
留 下 滿 目 瘡 瘍 的 雞 籠
Dodd's previous efforts
陶 德 在 這 一 年 的 努 力
went up in smoke.
全 部 化 為 火 有
The Sino-French War again
清 法 戰 爭 的 結 果
made the Ching Empire realize the importance of Taiwan as a
讓 清 常 國 再 一 次 體 認
shield of the mainland's southeastern coasts.
台 灣 對 屏 障 大 陸 東 南 海 域 的 重 要 性
Taiwan was thus elevated to the status of a province,
於 是 將 台 灣 升 格 為 一 個 省
Liu Ming-chuan became the first governor of Taiwan.
劉 銘 傳 成 為 台 灣 省 第 一 任 巡 撫
Liu noted that during the blockade in the
劉 銘 傳 鑒 於 清 法 戰 爭 封 鎖 期 間
Sino-French War, the absence of a telegraph system
困 為 缺 乏 電 報 系 統
hampered communications with the outside world.
志 澱 益 3 ﹕ 台 灣 無 法 與 外 界 溝 通 消 息
In 1887,
於 是 在 1887 年
the first undersea cable
建 造 台 灣 和 中 國 大 陸 之 間 的
was laid between Taiwan and the mainland China.
海 底 電 纜 線
For the first time, Taiwan
使 台 灣 首 度
became connected to the world's telegraph system.
與 世 界 電 報 傳 訊 系 統 連 結
Liu also began construction of the cross-island railroad.
劉 艷 傳 同 時 也 開 始 興 建 縱 貫 鐵 路
With Tataocheng as the hub, the rail system connected
鐵 路 以 大 稻 埕 為 中 心
Chilung to the north and Hsinchu to the south.
向 北 連 接 雞 籠 向 南 連 接 新 竹
In 1895,
美 國 記 者 Davidson
American reporter Davidson,
曾 經 在 1895 年 以
who worked for the North China Herald,
﹁ 北 華 捷 報 」 驛 台 記 者 的 身 份
came to cover Taiwan.
來 台 採 茲
He remembered vividly the events
他 對 當 時 這 條 鐵 路 工 程
surrounding the construction of the railway.
有 很 深 刻 的 印 別
The routes determined by the engineers were often changed.
工 程 師 所 測 定 的 路 線 常 被 改 變
The pale was often taken by the soldiers to use as firewood.
他 們 所 用 的 木 楝
There was an even grater problem though.
還 有 一 個 更 大 的 問 題
Corruption was in vogue.
就 是 賈 賂 風 氣 盛 行
In order to preserve the graves,
困 台 灣 人 害 怕 墳 墓 風 水 被 破 壤
the routes needed to have sudden curving to avoid them.
就 賭 賣 官 員 使 鐵 道 路 線 急 割 彎 曲 來 迴 避
Due to poor construction quality,
這 條 鐵 路 卻 困 為 施 工 不 良
the rail system was void of any practical value.
而 沒 有 太 大 的 實 用 價 值
Shortly after its completion,
建 成 後 不 久
the railroad was removed by the Japanese, Taiwan's new rulers.
就 被 台 灣 的 新 統 治 者 日 本 所 拆 了
After the Mutan Incident,
牡 丹 社 事 件 發 生 後
the Ching Empire sent
清 常 國 先 後 派 沈 葆 楨 和 岑 毓 莫
Shen Pao-chen and Tsen Yu-ying to Taiwan
到 台 灣 進 行 一 連 串
to develop the mountains and appease the aborigines,
以 ﹁ 開 山 擊 番 」 為 名 的 拓 壅 工 作
and use development of the mountains
以 開 發 山 地
to pay for increasing military expenses.
來 負 擔 日 漸 龐 大 的 軍 事 費 用
Because the mountain development policy
清 政 府 的 開 山 政 策
directly affected and intruded on
困 為 直 接 侵 略 到
the lives of the aborigines,
原 住 民 的 生 活 區 域
the policy was often met with strong resistance by the aborigines.
而 常 常 遭 到 原 住 民 的 激 烈 抵 抗
During Liu's administration,
到 了 劉 鑷 傳 主 政 時
the Ching took into account
清 政 府 配 合 茶葉
the flourishing tea leaf and camphor industries
和 樟 腦 產 業 的 興 起
to develop the interior mountains
在 內 山 的 拓 壅
using large-scale military operations.
開 始 動 用 大 規 模 的 軍 事 行 動 來 進 行
The Ching administration used the development of
甚 至 可 以 用
mountains to gain control over the aborigines.
開 山 撫 番 戰 爭 來 形 容
To develop the low-mountain areas
對 於 淺 山 地 帶 的 開 發
Liu Ming-chuan adopted the
劉 鑣 傳 掌 取
method of joint development with rich local gentries.
和 有 錢 士 紳 聯 手 開 發 的 方 式
The most prominent included
其 中 最 具 代 表 性 的
Lin Wei-yuan of Panchiao,
是 板 橋 的 林 維 源
Tataocheng merchant Li Chun-sheng,
大 稷 埕 的 洋 務 商 人 李 春 生
Miaoli landowner Huang Nan-chiu,
苗 栗 一 常 的 大 地 主 黃 南 球
and the rich and powerful Li Chao-tung from Wufeng.
和 霧 峰 的 富 豪 林 朝 榆
Among them, Lin Wei-yuan of Panchiao
其 中 板 橋 的 林 維 源
was the richest man in Taiwan at the time.
豆 ， 泰 2 是 當 時 台 灣 最 大 的 富 豪
His businesses included camphor, shipping, and private banking.
事 業 跨 足 樟 腦 、 航 運 和 錢 莊
The camphor oil extracted from trees
樟 樹 所 提 煉 出 來 的 樟 腦 油
was used as raw material for insect repellants,
可 以 用 來 做 驅 蟲 藥
perfume, medicine, and industrial products.
香 料 、 醫 學 、 工 業 等 原 料
Taiwan's camphor production at that time
台 灣 樟 腦 產 量
accounted for 80 percent of the global production.
佔 全 球 百 分 之 八 十
Camphor manufacturing was
樟 腦 製 造 業
one of the major industries in Taiwan.
是 當 時 台 灣 的 重 要 產 業 之 一
In his diary, British tea merchant Dodd
莢 國 茬 商 陶 德 曾 經 在 日 記 中
recounted how he had followed Hakka camphor workers
描 述 他 當 年 跟 隨 客 家 腦 丁
into the mountains to process camphor.
進 入 山 區 提 煉 樟 腦 的 經 驗
The Hakka camphor workers passed their days in horror.
客 家 腦 丁 每 天 提 頭 顱 過 生 活
If they were decapitated in a conflict with aboriginal warriors,
若 被 出 草 破 首
their Han employers would at most give them a simple burial
並 給 一 點 真 徵 性 的 撫 恤 銀
They wore aboriginal clothing and smoke pipes like the aboriginals.
腦 丁 們 身 穿 原 住 民 服
The only characteristic that distinguished them
唯 一 可 以 辨 識
from the aboriginals was their long braids.
他 們 不 是 原 住 民 的
Compared to camphor workers,
和 腦 丁 比 起 來
the aborigines were the major victims
原 住 民 更 是 這 種 開 壅 過 程 中
of the development process.
最 大 的 受 害 者
Liu on three occasions led the military to suppress
劉 鑣 傳 曾 經 三 度 親 自 揮 軍 征 討
the aborigines to facilitate mountain development.
為 的 就 是 要 順 利 完 成 開 山 任 務
Rich merchants of emerging industries
新 興 產 業 的 豪 商
also joined the suppression of the aborigines.
也 都 投 入 征 討 原 住 民 的 戰 爭
American reporter Davidson
美 國 記 者 Davidson
lived in Taiwan for eight years.
在 台 灣 居 住 八 年
The issue of camphor was also that of the raw barbarians.
對 於 樟 腦 問 題 也 就 是 生 番 問 題
In his book,
在 他 的 著 作 中
Davidson carefully analyzed the problem.
有 十 分 精 闢 的 分 析
To calculate the amount of camphor balls
去 演 算 貴 婧 寅 算 貴 婦 用 來 保 護 大 衣
was the result of how much blood of the people,
是 用 多 少 滴 人 血 的 代 價 換 來
or the camphor that could be used for curing rheumatism of the elderly,
或 者 醫 治 老 人 風 濕 症 的 樟 腦
is obtained by sacrificing how many human lives.
是 用 多 少 人 命 的 代 價 去 得 來
It was a really a tractive question.
是 一 個 值 得 深 思 的 問 題
The camphor tress could only grow in deep forests
困 為 樟 樹 就 只 生 長 在
also the home of Taiwan's hunters.
也 就 是 台 灣 獵 首 者 的 家 鄉
The crimes happen by taking advantage of all opportunities.
犯 罪 行 為 伺 機 而 生
But it was a pity that the violence did not come
而 且 很 遺 憾 的 是
but also the Han people,
漢 人 也 絕 不 錯 過
who took any chance to avenge on the wretched indigenous people.
對 不 幸 的 原 住 民 洩 憤 報 仇 的 機 會
Aborigines were driven out of the camphor forests,
原 住 民 被 迫 讓 出 樟 樹 林
and young aborigine children were sent to schools for them.
原 住 民 幼 童 被 送 入 番 學 堂
The government paid food and clothing to them monthly.
官 方 按 月 給 付 原 住 民 酒 食 衣 褲
The Ching Empire joined hands with wealthy merchants
清 常 國 與 豪 商 聯 手
to develop the camphor industry while exterminating
完 成 割 、 撫 、 墓
and pacifying the aborigines and cultivating the land.
並 行 的 產 業 開 發
The real beneficiaries were the wealthy merchants
蠕 正 得 利 的
who collaborated with the government.
是 結 交 官 府 的 地 方 豪 商
During this development process,
然 而 在 這 過 程 中
stories of the aborigines
原 住 民 族
protecting their ancestral homes
為 了 守 衛 他 們 傳 統 的 棲 息 地
and sacrificing their lives
而 付 出 生 命 的 歷 史
were ignored and forgotten.
卻 已 經 被 遺 忘
From the Opium War, Mutan Incident,
從 鴉 片 戰 爭 、 牡 丹 社 事 件
to the Sino-French War,
到 清 法 戰 爭
late 19th century Taiwan
台 灣 在 十 九 世 紀 末
had been prey for the
不 斷 成 為 東 、 西 洋 各 種 帝 國 主 義 勢 力
Eastern and Western imperial powers.
爭 相 蠶 食 的 地 方
To the descendants of the Han Chinese,
對 漢 人 的 後 代 子 孳 而 言
this had been a bitter and arduous
這 是 一 段 漫 長 與 辛 酸 的
saga of their ancestors.
先 民 開 拓 史
Yet to the original residents of the island,
但 是 對 這 個 島 上 原 來 的 主 人
the aborigines,
原 住 民 族 而 言
it was the beginning of a glum future.
卻 是 憎 慘 命 運 的 開 端
They were driven out of their ancestral homes
他 們 被 迪 遷 移 出 世 居 的 棲 息 地
and gradually lost their traditional culture.
也 逐 漸 遺 失 傳 統 的 文 化
As the administration on the island changed hands,
這 一 切 隨 著 島 上 政 權 的 轉 移
more drastic and dramatic changes would befall them.
又 將 有 更 激 恬 而 戲 劇 性 的 變 化